Finding Aid for Joe Lee Davis papers, 1918-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joe Lee Davis papers 1918-1976
Davis, Joe Lee, 1906-1974.
8 linear feet
90134 Aa 2
Professor of English at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, course materials, and writings; also collected materials of father, Lexington, Kentucky journalist, R. Lee Davis, and of brother T.O. Davis, a motion picture theater manager and author.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 7708 ) was the gift of Lorene Burke Davis, July 25, 1989.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Joe Lee Davis was born February 22, 1906 in Lexington, Kentucky, the son of Robert Lee and Jo Greene Davis. He graduated from the University of Kentucky receiving his B.A. degree in 1926 and his master of arts degree in 1927. For three years, Davis worked as an instructor in English at the University of Kentucky, then in 1930, he came to the University of Michigan where he received his doctorate in English in 1934. While a student, Davis was also a member of the U-M English department faculty, serving as an instructor from 1930 to 1937. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1937, associate professor in 1944, and professor in 1948.
As a teacher in the English department, Davis' specialties were American literature and 17th-century English literature. Professor Davis was a widely recognized authority on Ben Jonson and his contemporaries (the so-called "Sons of Ben"), as well as 20th-century authors James Branch Cabell and George Santayana. He was a prolific author, writing scholarly and popular articles on his specialties and American fiction in general. At the university, Davis helped to found the Program in American Culture and served as its chairman from 1952 to 1969.
Professor Joe Lee Davis died February 19, 1974.
The papers of Joe Lee Davis total 8 linear feet of correspondence, course materials, manuscripts of writings, and personal materials documenting his scholarly interests and skills as a teacher. Of added significance are collected family materials: journals and other papers of his father, Lexington, Kentucky journalist R. Lee Davis, his aunt Kate Davis, and his brother T. O. Davis, a motion picture theater manager and unpublished novelist.
Joe Lee Davis was a literary man who loved books and literary discussions. As a young man in Kentucky, he wrote poetry, articles for his father's newspapers, and essays on literary topics. The letters he wrote and received in the 1920s contain exchanges about books read and attempts at descriptive narrative. Davis and his correspondents in this period were honing their skills as writers through the medium of the letter. These letters are always interesting discussions of contemporary life, albeit somewhat pretentious in tone.
The largest portion of the collection are Davis' course materials consisting of files of notes and lectures on various authors, as well as other materials used in his specialized English classes. Of note, too, are manuscripts of Davis' writings, his master's and doctoral theses, and copies and manuscripts of his other writings (journal articles and newspaper book reviews).
The collected family materials are of interest for his father's journals covering family activities and his newspaper career in Lexington, and photographs of motion picture theaters in Kentucky and Ohio managed by his brother, Thomas O. Davis.
Subjects:
Kentucky.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Motion picture theaters--Kentucky--Ashland.; Motion picture theaters--Ohio--Cincinnati.; Motion picture theaters--Ohio--Columbus.; Keith Albee Palace Theatre (Columbus, Ohio); Lobbies--Ohio--Columbus.; Motion picture theaters.; Paramount Theatre (Ashland, Ky.)
Contributors:
Davis, Joe Lee.; Davis, R. Lee, 1868-1935.; Davis, Thomas O.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal and professional
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Memorials, obituaries, etc. 1974 (Box 1)
  - Personal miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Distinguished Faculty Award (letters sent to the nominating committee on Davis' behalf, 1974) (Box 1)
  - U-M Department of English Language and Literature
    - Executive committee minutes and miscellanea 1966-1974 (Box 1)
    - Search committee 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1918 (Box 1)
    - 1923-1930 (Box 1)
    - circa 1923-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1934-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1955 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1976 (Box 1)
    - re. Nominating Committee, American Literature Section, Modern Language Association 1966 (Box 1)
  - Log of books read, etc. 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - Early writings, poetry (Box 1)
  - Clippings of JLD newspaper poetry (Box 1)
  - Galley of book of poetry Boyhood Dreams (Box 1)
  - Student reading notes (University of Michigan)
    - "Some comedies of Mayne, Marmion, Dryden, and Shadwell with notes on Jonsonian influence" (Box 1)
    - "Reading notes, English 185-186" 1930 (Box 1)
    - "Reading notes in English 186" April 1931 (Box 1)
    - "Reading notes in English 186 (Second Series)" May 1931 (Box 1)
- Class materials
  - Authors file
    - Aiken, Conrad (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Sherwood (Box 1)
    - Asch, Sholem (Box 1)
    - Balzac, Honore de (Box 1)
    - Beck, Warren (Box 1)
    - Bennett, Arnold (Box 1)
    - Bowen, Elizabeth (Box 1)
    - Bronte family (Box 1)
    - Bronte, Anne The Tenant (Box 1)
    - Bronte, Charlotte (Box 1)
    - Brown, Charles B. (Box 1)
    - Bryant, William Cullen (Box 1)
    - Buck, Pearl (Box 1)
    - Butler, Samuel (Box 1)
    - Caldwell, Erskine (Box 1)
    - Camus, Albert (Box 1)
    - Cary, Joyce (Box 1)
    - Cather, Willa (Box 1)
    - Conrad, Joseph (Box 1)
    - Cooper, James F. (Box 1)
    - Crane, Stephen (Box 1)
    - Dickinson, Emily (Box 1)
    - Dos Passos, John (Box 2)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor (Box 2)
    - Dreiser, Theodore (Box 2)
    - Durrell, Lawrence (Box 2)
    - Eliot, George (Box 2)
    - Eliot, T.S. (Box 2)
    - Faulkner, William (Box 2)
    - Fisher, Vardis (Box 2)
    - Fitzgerald, F. Scott (Box 2)
    - Flaubert, Gustave (Box 2)
    - Forbes, Esther (Box 2)
    - Ford, Ford Madox (Box 2)
    - Forster, E.M. (Box 2)
    - Frost, Robert (Box 2)
    - Galsworthy, John (Box 2)
    - Gaskell, Mrs. (Elizabeth Cleghorn Gaskell) (Box 2)
    - Gerould, Katharine Fullerton (Box 2)
    - Greene, Graham (Box 2)
    - Guthrie, A.B. (Box 2)
    - Hamsun, Knut (Box 2)
    - Hardy, Thomas (Box 2)
    - Hawthorne, Nathaniel (Box 2)
    - Hemingway, Ernest (Box 2)
    - Howells, William Dean (Box 2)
    - Hudson, W.H. (Box 2)
    - Huxley, Aldous (Box 2)
    - Ibsen, Henrik (Box 2)
    - Irving, Washington (Box 2)
    - James, Henry (Box 2)
    - Joyce, James (Box 2)
    - Kafka, Franz (Box 2)
    - Koestler, Arthur (Box 2)
    - Lanier, Sidney (Box 2)
    - Lawrence, D.H. (Box 2)
    - Lindsay, Vachel (Box 2)
    - Lermontov, Mikhail (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Sinclair (Box 2)
    - Lloyd, John (Box 2)
    - London, Jack (Box 2)
    - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth (Box 2)
    - Mann, Thomas (Box 2)
    - Marquand, John P. (Box 2)
    - Maugham, W. Somerset (Box 2)
    - Maupassant, Guy de (Box 2)
    - Melville, Herman (Box 2)
    - Meredith, George (Box 2)
    - Merrick, Leonard (Box 2)
    - Moore, George (Box 2)
    - Moravia, A. (Box 2)
    - Norris, Frank (Box 2)
    - O'Neill, Eugene (Box 2)
    - Poe, Edgar A. (Box 2)
    - Powys, T.F. (Box 2)
    - Proust, Marcel (Box 2)
    - Richardson, Dorothy (Box 2)
    - Richardson, Samuel (Box 2)
    - Robinson, Edwin A. (Box 2)
    - Saltus, Edgar (Box 2)
    - Santayana, George (Box 2)
    - Shakespeare, William (Box 2)
    - Shaw, George Bernard (Box 2)
    - Silone, Ignazio (Box 2)
    - Stendhal (Henri Beyle) (Box 2)
    - Stowe, Harriet Beecher (Box 2)
    - Swift, Jonathan (Box 2)
    - Thackeray, William M. (Box 2)
    - Thoreau, Henry David (Box 2)
    - Tolstoy, Leo (Box 2)
    - Trollope, Anthony (Box 2)
    - Turgenev, Ivan (and other Russian writers) (Box 2)
    - Twain, Mark (Box 2)
    - Ward, Mrs. Humphry (Box 2)
    - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 2)
    - Wassermann, Jacob (Box 2)
    - Wells, H.G. (Box 2)
    - Whitman, Walt (Box 2)
    - Wilde, Oscar (Box 2)
    - Wolfe, Thomas (Box 2)
    - Woolf, Maritta (Box 2)
    - Woolf, Virginia (Box 2)
    - Wright, Richard (Box 2)
    - Zola, Emile (Box 2)
  - Subject files
    - Eighteenth Century America (Box 2)
    - Lectures (various topics) (Box 2)
    - "Negro novel in America" (Box 2)
    - New criticism (Box 2)
    - "New Deal" in poetry (Box 2)
    - Parodies (Box 2)
    - Poems for quotations (Box 2)
    - Psychology and literature (Box 2)
    - Regionalism, American (Box 2)
    - Renaissance drama (Box 2)
    - Science fiction (Box 2)
  - Lectures, papers, notes, etc.
    - American Literature-From Beginnings to 1870, 2 expandable folders (Box 3)
    - Pro-seminar in renaissance drama, 2 expandable folders (Box 3)
    - The English Novel, 1 expandable folder (Box 3)
    - Contemporary drama, 1 expandable folder (Box 3)
    - Shakespeare lectures (Box 4)
    - English 170 (Poetry) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous files
      - Critical and other material for novel (Box 4)
      - Play problems (outline) (Box 4)
      - Poems (Box 4)
      - Poetry lectures (various) (Box 4)
      - Recent fiction: a list (Box 4)
      - Syllabus, etc. (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Essays on Contemporary Letters, 1927-1930 (Box 4)
    (includes master's thesis, 1927, entitled "Stuart Pratt Sherman as a literary critic")
  - Thesis: "The 'Sons of Ben' in English Realistic Comedy, 1625-1642" 1934, 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - "Sons of Ben" research notebook (Box 4)
  - Reviews and reports on "Sons of Ben" (Box 4)
    (Davis edited his thesis for publication by Wayne State University Press)
  - Manuscripts of writings (pre-1930), 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts of writings (various), 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts of writings (mainly "On reading novels") (Box 5)
  - Manuscript: "Approaches and encounters in American Studies" (Box 5)
  - Manuscript: American Literature (Box 5)
  - Manuscript: "The case for comedy in Caroline theatrical apologetics" (Box 5)
  - Manuscript: "Quarrel with darkness" (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts: "Santayana as a critic of transcendentalism" (and other essays on Santayana) (Box 5)
  - Book reviews (manuscripts of reviews and clippings of the published reviews) (Box 5)
  - Reprints of articles and periodicals containing articles written by JLD, 2 expandable folders (Box 6)
  - Microfilm of writings
    - "The Caroline 'Sons of Ben' in Comedy", positive and negative microfilm (Box 6)
      (reworking of thesis)
  - Microfilm of writings
    - "Quarrel with Darkness; Essays in Literary Criticism and American Studies", positive and negative microfilm (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Jokes (Box 6)
  - Limericks (Box 6)
  - Parodies (Box 6)
- Davis family
  - Kate Davis (JLD aunt): Scrapbooks, 3 volumes (Box 7)
    (scrapbooks consist of newspaper articles by R. Lee Davis, entitled "Reminiscences of Prominent Kentuckians," articles about Kentucky people and happenings, etc.)
  - R. Lee Davis (JLD father)
    - Journals and diaries 1929-1935, 3 volumes (Box 7)
    - Scrapbooks, 6 volumes (Box 7)
      (scrapbooks consist of newspaper articles that he wrote and other articles that he found of interest)
    - Poems and letter (Box 7)
    - Clippings (Box 7)
    - Photograph (Box 7)
  - T.O. Davis (JLD brother)
    - Photographs re career as manager of motion picture theaters in Kentucky and Ohio, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Writings (general) (Box 8)
    - Novel: Julia Farnum, 2 versions (in 4 boxes) (Box 8)
    - Correspondence with publishers re novel Julia Farnum (Box 8)